<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached to the nobely-deseruing gentleman, Sir Thomas Warner And the rest of his companie: bound to the West-Indies. For their farevvell: At St. Buttolphs, Aldersgate, London. Septemb. 6. 1629. By Iohn Featly, Preacher of the Word of God.</title>
            <title>Sermon preached to the nobely-deserving gentleman, Sir Thomas Warner.</title>
            <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00608</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115123</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850342</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850342</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15534</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00608)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 793:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached to the nobely-deseruing gentleman, Sir Thomas Warner And the rest of his companie: bound to the West-Indies. For their farevvell: At St. Buttolphs, Aldersgate, London. Septemb. 6. 1629. By Iohn Featly, Preacher of the Word of God.</title>
                  <title>Sermon preached to the nobely-deserving gentleman, Sir Thomas Warner.</title>
                  <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nicholas Bourne, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached to the West-India Company.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf probably blank--Folger catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15534:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15534:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED TO THE NOBELY-DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SERVING GENTLEMAN, SIR THOMAS WARNER: And the reſt of his Companie: Bound to the <hi>Weſt-Indies. For their</hi> FAREVVELL:</p>
            <p>At St. <hi>Buttolphs, Alderſgate, London.</hi> Septemb. 6. 1629.</p>
            <p>BY IOHN FEATLY, Preacher of <hi>the Word of GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> at the South entrance of the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15534:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15534:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, IAMES Earle of <hi>Carlile, &amp;c. Count Palatine</hi> of the Prouince of CARLILE, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Vtie</hi> becomes diſguiſed, where it wants the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Integrity:</hi> and this loſes it ſelfe, when ignorant of <hi>expreſſion. Great Perſonages</hi> are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten cloyed (as with the <hi>verball expreſſions,</hi> ſo) with the hypocriſie of thoſe that tender them. But my <hi>ſelfe</hi> am become the <hi>exception</hi> againſt that common rule; and I dare with as bold a Confidence convict, as ſlight the
<pb facs="tcp:15534:3"/> 
               <hi>Oppoſer.</hi> My bowing-heart hath bin alwaies ſteep'd in deſire to preſent the <hi>Pledge</hi> of an humble <hi>obſeruance</hi> to your <hi>Lordſhip:</hi> But remaining guilty of my <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> here I ſue for <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> by a Noble <hi>Protection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Sermon</hi> it ſelfe is the <hi>Defenders</hi> of the <hi>faith;</hi> and though briefe, yet <hi>orthodox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</hi> If any carpe at it, peraduenture it may proue a <hi>Manſenile-apple,</hi> (whereof I haue ſeene diuers in the <hi>Indies</hi>) that bliſters the <hi>Tongues</hi> of them that taſte.</p>
            <p>The Noble worth of my deſeruing <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, Sir Thomas Warner,</hi> made me a <hi>Traueller</hi> into the <hi>Indies,</hi> being thereby the firſt <hi>Preacher</hi> vpon <hi>Saint Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Ilands.</hi> And your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> vnualu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Goodneſſe and <hi>Patronage</hi> of thoſe <hi>Parts,</hi> hath now commanded this <hi>Sermon</hi> to trauell into the <hi>Cenſure</hi> of each <hi>Peruſer:</hi> If it ſuffer by a Martyrdome, yet the <hi>Author</hi> ſhall euer appeare</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humbly and faithfully-deuoted, IO. FEATLY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15534:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED TO THE <hi>Weſt-Jndia Company.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOSH. 1.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Haue not I commanded thee? Onely be ſtrong, and of a good courage: Be not afraid, neither bee diſmayed: for I will be with thee whitherſoeuer thou goeſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y <hi>Text</hi> ſpeakes in Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and like the rowſing Drum beates an Alarum: <hi>Ioſhua</hi> is the <hi>Commander,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> his <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Promiſe</hi> are the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> whoſe <hi>destruction</hi> is threatned by the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Warre.</hi> Heere are <hi>Iudgements</hi> to be executed, and furious <hi>Anger</hi> to be fed with the Blood of a Nation, and the deſolation of a <hi>Country.</hi> The diſmall day of a grim deſtruction, that muſt ſpeake in the fierceſt language of horror and amazement, is now hard at hand. And that the <hi>Time</hi> it ſelfe may (as it
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15534:4"/> were) ſtand ſtill till the gaſping groanes of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men haue myſtied the Ayre, and their foa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my blood disfigured the Earth, the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſhall ſeeme vniuſt to the conquered wretches, when each minute of vnexpected <hi>Miſery</hi> ſhall appeare more tedious then an Age of common Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> after a tyring and long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Iourney, grow ſo weary, that their faint limbes are now as deſirous of <hi>Reſt,</hi> as before their ſcorching <hi>Thirſt</hi> deſired <hi>Water:</hi> Yet, leſt they ſhould enioy their <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> before their <hi>Miſeries</hi> had prepared a ſufficient reliſh for them, they muſt not yet enter into their earthly <hi>Bliſſe:</hi> For behold their <hi>Commander</hi> is dead; and what greater Affliction could ſtrike them dumbe with ouer-cloyed Sorrow, then the loſſe of him, who ſhould leade them to their <hi>Reſt?</hi> yet to the end that they might know that he that commanded their <hi>Ruler,</hi> commands them to behold his <hi>Prouidence</hi> and <hi>Care</hi> ouer them; <hi>Moſes is dead,</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. of this <hi>Chap.</hi>) But what followes? <hi>Now therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe Ioſhua, goe ouer this Iordan, thou and all this People, vnto the Land which I doe giue vnto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt the <hi>People</hi> ſhould ſuſpect their <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Commiſsion,</hi> it is giuen him by the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> in the 5, 6, 7, and 8. verſes, but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the former and later words of my <hi>Text: Haue not I commanded thee?</hi> and <hi>I will bee with thee whitherſoeuer thou goeſt.</hi> Yea, and to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſhould not bee ignorant of his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15534:4"/> 
               <hi>dutie</hi> required, the <hi>Almighty</hi> (as it were) puts in the <hi>Conditions, Onely be ſtrong, and of a good courage; Bee not afraid, neither be diſmaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus is my <hi>Text</hi> the compleat <hi>Commiſsion: Haue not I, &amp;c.</hi> The words imply a <hi>Voyage</hi> to make warre vpon a reiected <hi>Nation:</hi> I may therefore peraduenture incurre the rigid Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of diuers heere preſent, whoſe home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Security deſires to nuzle it ſelfe in the ſweet repoſe of a happy <hi>Peace.</hi> And may the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> preſerue our Kingdome in the <hi>Bond</hi> of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quietneſſe</hi> till our <hi>Sauiours</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Comming. Yet I am ſure of <hi>Others</hi> that heare me this day, which cannot diſlike the Subiect of my enſuing <hi>Sermon.</hi> My <hi>Text</hi> was choſen for ſome of <hi>vs</hi> moſt particularly, whoſe occaſions command vs to take leaue of our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Soile,</hi> that we may poſſeſſe the Land of the <hi>Hittites</hi> and <hi>Amorites,</hi> the Habitations of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage-Heathens,</hi> whoſe vnderſtandings were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet illuminated with the knowledge of their <hi>Maker.</hi> Yet will we not ingroſſe the whole houres diſcourſe: For I preſume (by Gods aſſiſtance) that my <hi>Meditations</hi> ſhall bee acceptable to All, and the <hi>vſe</hi> profitable: for euery one ought to deſire and endeuour that his <hi>Actions</hi> might be ſeconded with <hi>diuine Bleſsings,</hi> if he deſire what hee ought: Which <hi>he</hi> alone can doe, whoſe <hi>approbation</hi> wee muſt implore, that ſo wee may heare him ſpeaking vnto <hi>vs,</hi> as to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in my <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:15534:5"/>
            <p>The <hi>words</hi> (you ſee) are full of <hi>authority,</hi> and containe in them
<list>
                  <item>thus much <hi>Variety:</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander: I: God.</hi> wherein,
<list>
                              <item>1. <hi>The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion and Authoritie he giues to</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua: <hi>Haue not I commanded, &amp;c.</hi> Wherein obſerue
<list>
                                    <item>1. <hi>His Power,</hi> included in the <hi>Maieſty of his ſpeech.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2. <hi>His prouidence and care ouer his People,</hi> to giue them <hi>Ioſhua.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>A Promiſe.</hi> wherein
<list>
                                    <item>1. <hi>The Promiſe</hi> it ſelfe; to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> vpon his truſty <hi>Seruice: I will bee with thee.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>2. <hi>The large extenſion of it: Whitherſoeuer thou goeſt.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Be ſtrong, and of a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                       <hi>Be not afraid, neither be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>The Perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, Ioſhua:</hi> in whom is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <hi>a Duty.</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>1. <hi>Affirmatiue.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. <hi>Negatiue.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt of the firſt Generall, the <hi>Commander:</hi> and therein of the <hi>Commiſſion:</hi> in which Gods great <hi>Power,</hi> included in the Maieſtie of his Speech. <hi>Haue not I commanded thee?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EArthly Authority</hi> deriues it ſelfe from the <hi>Omnipotency,</hi> and ceaſes to be <hi>imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> when it forgets the <hi>Author</hi> thereof. <hi>Non eſt Poteſtas niſi a Deo; &amp; quae ſunt Poteſtates, ſunt a Deo ordinatae</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.1.) There is no <hi>Power,</hi> but of <hi>God;</hi> and the <hi>Powers</hi> that are made, are ordained of <hi>God.</hi> Here then <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſtands iuſtified, whoſe Command knew no other <hi>donor</hi> then the great Commander of <hi>Heauen</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> And againe, here <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15534:5"/> confutes the <hi>Epicures,</hi> by his owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, making vſe of his <hi>Potencie</hi> in the words of my <hi>Text.</hi> Could any man heere queſtion his <hi>All-ſufficient Power</hi> in doing whatſoeuer he pleaſeth, the <hi>maieſtie</hi> of his words would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule the petulancie of ſuch blind follie: <hi>Haue not I commanded thee? I</hi> that ſit in the high and holy place, to iudge thoſe <hi>Miſcreants,</hi> that dare queſtion mine <hi>Authority. I,</hi> that haue created all things out of nothing, that nothing might hinder them from knowing their <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. I,</hi> that threaten in <hi>Thunder,</hi> when vniuſt <hi>Mortals,</hi> following their owne wickedneſſe, prouoke my fury to throw <hi>vengeance</hi> vpon their <hi>diſobedience. I,</hi> that controule the whole <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke of Nature,</hi> and can blow it away with the breath of my <hi>diſpleaſure. Haue not I commanded thee?</hi> The <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of his <hi>Stile</hi> is a ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Sufficiencie</hi> of his <hi>Power,</hi> againſt all that deny it. To reade his <hi>Iudgements</hi> vpon the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their Iourney, for their ſtubborne <hi>Murmurings,</hi> would command the <hi>Peruſer</hi> to a confident beliefe of his <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> To behold the <hi>Plagues</hi> he ſent vpon K. <hi>Pharoah</hi> and all <hi>Egypt,</hi> would make the <hi>heathens</hi> themſelues deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of his <hi>Prerogatiue-royall.</hi> Yea, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his infinite ſtore of ſeuerall Puniſhments for peruerſe <hi>Sinners,</hi> would make the ſtubbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>offender</hi> acknowledge it ſufficient when he ſhall ſay <hi>Haue not I commanded thee?</hi> Let <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> then ſtand vndaunted, and the glory of the <hi>Creator</hi> diſpell the Clouds of <hi>Feare</hi> that might
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15534:6"/> poſſeſſe his Heart, for it is the great <hi>Iehouah</hi> that commands him. It will not (I ſuppoſe) be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent here to inſtruct the <hi>ignorant</hi> in this <hi>Attribute</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which is defined to bee the <hi>eſſentiall</hi> property of <hi>God,</hi> whereby he can and may worke whatſoeuer is agreeable to his <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> Yet that the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God</hi> hath ſeuerall <hi>acceptions.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt it is taken for the Eternall <hi>Sonne</hi> of <hi>God, Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> (as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.) <hi>We preach Chriſt the Power of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, for the <hi>Goſpell</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.) <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpell of Chriſt, for it is the Power of God vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly <hi>Catachreſtically,</hi> The <hi>Samaritanes</hi> called <hi>Simon Magus</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>GOD, (Acts</hi> 8.10.) <hi>To whom they all gaue heede, from the leaſt vnto the greateſt, ſaying, This man is the great Power of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, and truely, It is taken for the <hi>eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Property of God,</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Trinitie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Yet, to auoyde all erroneous miſtaking here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, we muſt haue a care to diſtinguiſh betweene the <hi>Eſsentiall-Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> (now ſpoken of) and the <hi>Perſonall-Power:</hi> As the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting,</hi> in the <hi>Father;</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of being <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goten,</hi> in the <hi>Sonne;</hi> and the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>Proceeding,</hi> in the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe, wee muſt diſtinguiſh betweene the <hi>abſolute</hi> and the <hi>actuall Omnipotencie</hi> of <hi>God;</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15534:6"/> yet both remaining <hi>actiue.</hi> The former is ſuch whereby God can perfectly <hi>doe</hi> whatſoeuer may be done, as well <hi>praeter &amp; ſuper naturam,</hi> beſides and aboue nature, as with it: exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in making <hi>Elizabeth</hi> conceiue in her <hi>old age,</hi> and the like: for <hi>with God all things are poſſible, Luk.</hi> 1.37. The latter is that whereby hee not onely can doe whatſoeuer hee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines; but can doe it with a <hi>word,</hi> without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulty, and nothing may or can reſiſt him. From the former of theſe ariſeth a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Whether <hi>God</hi> can bring to paſſe things <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Nature,</hi> ſtiled <hi>Impoſſibilities?</hi> To which we muſt diſtinguiſh betweene <hi>Impoſsibilia natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae,</hi> and <hi>Impoſsibilia naturâ,</hi> Things impoſſible of <hi>Nature</hi> to be done, which flye beyond the common pitch thereof, as to make the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſtand ſtill; or cauſe the <hi>fire</hi> not to burne, which we reade of in the Scriptures; And things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible in Nature, which are againſt the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of a thing, as it is <hi>Ens:</hi> as to make a thing ſimply and really to bee, and not to bee at the ſame inſtant, which is vtterly and abſolutely <hi>impoſsible.</hi> By this latter the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted, which maintaine the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> of <hi>Bread,</hi> into the very <hi>fleſhly Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and make the very indiuiduall Body in ſeuerall places at once. Thus much then for the <hi>Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> knowledge; Giue me leaue onely to cleere 2 or 3 <hi>objections,</hi> and ſo I ſhall conclude it.</p>
               <p>Firſt then in <hi>Geneſis</hi> 18.17. the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid, <hi>Can I hide from Abraham the thing which I doe?</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15534:7"/> (as ſome Tranſlations reade it) which may ſeeme to deny his <hi>Omnipotency:</hi> This is eaſily anſwered by the <hi>word,</hi> which is in the future tenſe, and our laſt Tranſlation iuſtly renders it, <hi>Shall I hide?</hi> Or if the former were true, yet it would be <hi>per</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not that <hi>God</hi> could not hide from <hi>Abraham</hi> the deſtruction of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> but in the ardencie of his affection, that he was ſo good that he would not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.22. When God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Lot</hi> to fly to <hi>Zoar,</hi> he ſpake in theſe words, <hi>Haſte thee, eſcape thither, for I cannot doe any thing till thou eſcape thither:</hi> therefore the <hi>Omnipotencie</hi> may ſeeme to be queſtioned: But to this it is anſwered, that God ſaid hee could not, becauſe his Councell was vnchangeable, and he had before determined the eſcape of iuſt <hi>Lot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, Becauſe <hi>God</hi> cannot lye, nor ſinne, nor be deceiued, nor dye, therefore ſome would queſtion his all-ſufficient <hi>Power:</hi> But to this S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> anſwers, <hi>Ita haec non poteſt, vt potius ſi poſſet, minoris eſſet poteſtatis.</hi> Could he admit of theſe things, it would inſtead of <hi>improuing, leſſen</hi> his <hi>Power.</hi> He is called <hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent,</hi> becauſe he can <hi>doe what he will,</hi> and not <hi>ſuffer what he will not;</hi> for that would proue a <hi>paſſiue-Power</hi> in God, which we abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to be in him, and acknowledge onely that which is <hi>actiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus haue I, as briefly as I might, waded
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15534:7"/> through the firſt particular, conſidered in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua's Commiſsion, viZ.</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of his Speech: Now followes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Prouidence of GOD, <hi>pointed out in his</hi> Care <hi>which he had ouer his</hi> People, <hi>in giuing them</hi> Ioſhua, Thee: Haue not I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COrruptio vnius eſt generatio alterius,</hi> ſay the <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> The Corruption of one thing, is the Generation of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>Seede</hi> in the ground quickens by <hi>death.</hi> The <hi>Aſhes</hi> of the <hi>Phoenix</hi> produceth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Bird.</hi> And as in them, ſo likewiſe in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: Moſes</hi> being dead, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſucceeds. Thus will the Word of God euer haue the <hi>Truth</hi> to ſupport it. He promiſed the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whoſe <hi>Commander</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, (leſt they ſhould rowte themſelues with a <hi>Mutinie,</hi> to daſh their hopes,) <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> is placed ouer them by <hi>Diuine Authority.</hi> Thus was the <hi>Prouidence</hi> of God as well manifeſted in this, as in former paſſages touching the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites.</hi> His <hi>Prouidence</hi> (I ſay) which that I may briefly handle, I ſhall conſider therein,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>What it is</hi> in the largeſt extent, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>All-mighty,</hi> whereby he did <hi>create,</hi> and doth, and will <hi>gouerne,</hi> and <hi>preſerue</hi> by his Word, all his <hi>Creatures</hi> in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15534:8"/> but more eſpecially <hi>Thoſe that belieue</hi> in his Word, to whom he giues the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> for their <hi>Protector.</hi> Other <hi>definitions</hi> I neede not oppreſſe you with, leſt I ſhould become tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>Secondly, wee muſt conſider <hi>How wee may know that there is ſuch a Prouidence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is manifeſted
<list>
                     <item>1. By the <hi>order</hi> of things <hi>viſible.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. By the conſideration of <hi>God</hi> in himſelfe.</item>
                     <item>3. By his <hi>Gouerning</hi> of all things, manifeſtly appearing.</item>
                     <item>4. By his <hi>Word,</hi> wherein in diuers places he hath made it euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apparent.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Cauſes</hi> are to bee weighed; which are <hi>Three, viZ.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Mercie of GOD.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Promiſe of GOD.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The Goodneſſe and Loue of GOD.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Fourthly. The <hi>Sorts</hi> of it, which are two, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Generall,</hi> whereby GOD preſerues all things in generall.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Speciall,</hi> whereby he doth more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly tender the <hi>Faithfull.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Fiftly and laſtly, The <hi>Effects</hi> of it, which are two-fold, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Generall,</hi> to <hi>Create, Gouerne, Preſerue, Cheriſh,</hi> and <hi>Defend vs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15534:8"/>
                  <item>2. <hi>Speciall,</hi> to his owne <hi>Elect,</hi> in giuing them his <hi>holy Spirit</hi> as a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer,</hi> and in <hi>caring</hi> both for their <hi>Soules</hi> and <hi>Bodies.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Thus you ſee here <hi>Gods</hi> eſpeciall <hi>Prouidence</hi> ouer the <hi>Children of Iſrael,</hi> his choſen <hi>People,</hi> who for his <hi>Mercie-ſake,</hi> his <hi>Promiſe-ſake,</hi> and through his <hi>Loue,</hi> would not ſuffer them to wander vp and downe without a <hi>Guide;</hi> but vpon the <hi>death</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he puts <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in his ſtead, and giues him his <hi>Charge,</hi> with an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, Haue not I commanded thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereſoeuer <hi>GOD</hi> layes an <hi>Iniunction,</hi> he cannot, nay, he will not endure any <hi>Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> His <hi>Authority</hi> will not bee queſtioned, therefore his <hi>will</hi> muſt be obeyed. <hi>Haue not I commanded thee?</hi> True, yet this Command is louing too, and out of that <hi>affection</hi> which hee had both to the <hi>People</hi> and to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> whom he firſt inſtructed, and then preferred.</p>
               <p>I could here remember the <hi>forwardneſſe</hi> of our <hi>Times,</hi> wherein ſome, not knowing the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of <hi>Authority,</hi> thinke themſelues happy to weare the <hi>fauour</hi> of a <hi>Title,</hi> yet remaining ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in the <hi>dutie</hi> attending it. <hi>Honour</hi> was neuer more then a blaſt, which whiſtleth vp and downe, and rather ſtudieth <hi>Faſhions</hi> then <hi>Goodneſse:</hi> it is indeed a meere <hi>Ignis fatuus,</hi> leading men out of the right way, and yet ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as bright as if it meant no deceipt. This <hi>Age</hi> is as well read in <hi>Titles,</hi> as any euer was in former times; but whether they haue all had
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15534:9"/> their <hi>Authority</hi> from the <hi>Almighty,</hi> (as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in my <hi>Text</hi>) with their <hi>Commiſsion</hi> from <hi>Heauen,</hi> running in the Style of my <hi>Theame, Haue not I commanded thee?</hi> I queſtion whether I may queſtion. Great Perſons in <hi>Honour,</hi> I am ſure, are ſometimes but like to the <hi>Line</hi> of an <hi>Angle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod:</hi> the <hi>Corke</hi> is the <hi>Honour,</hi> floting on the top of the Water, yet giuing notice where the <hi>Bait</hi> is, which muſt catch that <hi>Fiſh,</hi> which we commonly in our language call <hi>Vice.</hi> There are ſeuerall kindes thereof: Somtimes <hi>Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery</hi> nibbles at the <hi>Baite;</hi> oftentimes <hi>Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse;</hi> but for the moſt part <hi>Pride:</hi> But where <hi>Deſert</hi> challenges the preferment of <hi>Honour,</hi> the <hi>Lead</hi> ſo peizes the <hi>Corke,</hi> that it is iuſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene floating and ſinking, yet not enclining to one more then the other. He that thus conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with himſelfe of the <hi>Honour</hi> hee hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; not purchaſed, but merited, ſhall not only haue his <hi>Commiſsion</hi> with <hi>Ioſhua, Haue not I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee?</hi> but ſhall likewiſe haue the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> with <hi>Ioſhua</hi> too, <hi>I will be with thee whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou goeſt.</hi> Which is</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part of the firſt generall: <hi>and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in firſt of the</hi> Promiſe <hi>it ſelfe,</hi> I will bee with thee.</head>
               <p>THe power of <hi>Vbiquity</hi> belongs to the <hi>Deity</hi> onely; and determines that <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to bee moſt irreligiouſly <hi>ignorant</hi> that dares a <hi>contradiction.</hi> That <hi>Spirit</hi> which in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15534:9"/> the beginning moued vpon the <hi>waters,</hi> will waſh the <hi>Peruerſe</hi> into the extremity of <hi>Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of <hi>repentant teares</hi> pleads his <hi>reconciliation. Sparrows</hi> cannot take a flight, nor a <hi>haire</hi> fall from the <hi>head,</hi> till <hi>God</hi> hath granted a <hi>conſent.</hi> The <hi>Scripture</hi> takes notice of theſe two <hi>Inſtances,</hi> as things vnder-valued in our opinion; yet the former may teach vs by his flight, to ſoare aloft, and ſhun that <hi>nakednes</hi> wherwith we are cloathed; as well as the latter may proue the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Prouidence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who can blow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that which wee cannot ſo much as diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; <hi>Gods Immenſitie</hi> is without <hi>circumſcription;</hi> his <hi>vbiquity</hi> without <hi>contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> his <hi>Omni-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> without <hi>limitation:</hi> His <hi>Attributes</hi> haue all a relation each to other, and remaine indiſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Were he not <hi>Omni-preſent,</hi> we might deny his <hi>Omnipotencie,</hi> becauſe he would not haue <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer</hi> then, to be <hi>euery-where:</hi> we might deny his <hi>Omni-ſcience,</hi> becauſe he could not know the <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> of men, where he could not be. And thus ſhould we ſo mangle the <hi>Diuinity,</hi> that by ſuch Conſequences we ſhould in our opinions euen vtterly diſſolue it. How miſerable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we might become, being left to our ſelues, denying a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happines of <hi>Immortality,</hi> and expecting no more <hi>Bliſſe</hi> hereafter, iudge ye. I could amplifie this point far more largely, but that I hope your true beliefe would iudge it impertinent. Let our Poſition then be that of S. <hi>Austin, (Lib.</hi> 22. <hi>De Ciuit. Dei) Deus totus in Coelo eſt, &amp; totus in Terrâ, non alternis temporibus, ſed vtrum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſimul.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15534:10"/> Or as the ſame <hi>Father,</hi> in his 57. <hi>Epiſtle: Deus eſt totus vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, et totus in vnoquo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, &amp; totus in Seipſo.</hi> God is all and wholly, euery where, and the ſame in euery perſon and place, and that in himſelfe. The <hi>Heauens</hi> containe him, or elſe we cannot begin the <hi>Lords-Prayer, Our Father which art in Heauen.</hi> And yet he is not limited and bounded within that place; for ſo we ſhould deny him to be heere vpon <hi>Earth,</hi> and how miſerable <hi>Mortals</hi> would then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, let euery man cenſure. GOD is in <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> in reſpect of his more ample <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> becauſe hee doth there moſt excellently make manifeſt his <hi>Power, Wiſdome, Goodneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Communication</hi> of his <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> in the preſence of the bleſſed <hi>Angels.</hi> We muſt vnderſtand of him, as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> doe of the <hi>Soule,</hi> who ſay it it <hi>Tota in toto, &amp; tota in quâlibet parte:</hi> It is all compleatly in the whole Body, yea, and the ſame in euery part: In the <hi>Hands, Armes, Legs, Feete,</hi> and the like; but the chiefe Seate of it is the <hi>Head,</hi> as the <hi>Galen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts;</hi> but according to <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and <hi>Diuines,</hi> the <hi>Heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus (Beloued) GOD is vpon <hi>Earth,</hi> ſeeing and obſeruing what we doe, ordering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of vs according to his pleaſure; yea, and he is in <hi>Hell,</hi> executing and viewing there the effects of his vnſpeakable <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> But his <hi>Chaire</hi> of <hi>Eſtate</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeak) is aboue in the <hi>Heauens; Nuſquam eſt, quatenus a nullo contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: et vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt, quatenus Omnia continet.</hi> He
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15534:10"/> is no where as contained, and he is euery where as he containes all things. Hee is euery where entire in himſelfe, and abſent from none, yet he is not contained by thoſe with whom he is preſent, as if he could not be without them. He is euery where by his preſence, ſo as all things euer haue, doe, and ſhall ſtand naked to his view. And laſtly, hee is euery where by his <hi>Vertue,</hi> working and effecting his good pleaſure. Thus then haue we determined of the <hi>Omni-preſence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the ſame <hi>eſſentiall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here we renounce the Errors of the <hi>Vbiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians,</hi> who haue earneſtly contended to proue the <hi>vbiquity</hi> of <hi>Chriſts humanity;</hi> but how vaine their <hi>Tenent</hi> is, let S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeake, who in his 57 Epiſtle thus concludes of it, <hi>Vna perſona De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp; homo eſt, &amp; vter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt vnus Chriſtus Ieſus, vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> per id quod Deus eſt, in Coelo autem per id quod homo. God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> make vp but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, both of them vnited being the one <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> who is euery where as he is <hi>God,</hi> but in <hi>Heauen</hi> only as he is <hi>Man.</hi> I dare not ſpend any time in the Arguments <hi>Pro &amp; Contra</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this point.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Vſe</hi> may be that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, (Pſal.</hi> 139.7) <hi>Quo irem a Spiritu tuo? aut quo a facie tuâ fugerem?</hi> Whither ſhall we goe then from thy <hi>Spirit?</hi> or whither ſhall we fly from thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? He that is <hi>Omni-ſcient,</hi> knowes what we are: Hee that is <hi>Omni-potent</hi> hath cauſed that we are: and he that is <hi>Omni-preſent,</hi> is, and <hi>will be with vs whitherſoeuer we goe,</hi> (according
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15534:11"/> to the words of my <hi>Text,) I,</hi> the great <hi>Iehouah,</hi> who haue <hi>Heauen</hi> for my <hi>Throne,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> for my <hi>Foot-ſtoole;</hi> who know all things, gouerne &amp; diſpoſe of euery thing according to my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; from whom no place is hid, and without whom no place can be; <hi>I</hi> (I ſay) will bee with thee <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> in this thy progreſſe to the <hi>Land</hi> of <hi>Canaan; I will be with thee directiuely,</hi> to teach thee <hi>what thou ſhalt doe: I will be with thee po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully,</hi> to giue thee ability of performance, and to cheere thee vp in thy <hi>Voyage.</hi> Yea, <hi>I will bee with thee correctiuely,</hi> to puniſh thoſe which diſobey my Command, ſent vnto them by <hi>thee. I will be with thee without intermiſsion of time;</hi> when thou ſleepeſt, and when thou awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, when thou walkeſt on the way, when thou goeſt before the <hi>People</hi> which I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thee, and when thou <hi>entreſt</hi> with them into the Land of <hi>Promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Happy <hi>Iſraelites!</hi> whoſe <hi>Protector</hi> was <hi>God,</hi> and whoſe indulgent <hi>Father</hi> was the Lord of <hi>Hoſts.</hi> Thrice happy <hi>Ioſhua</hi> too! whoſe <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> was <hi>from the Lord, ſtrong and mighty, euen from the Lord, mighty in Battell,</hi> who firſt gaue him <hi>ability</hi> to performe, and then the <hi>order</hi> of performance. So iuſt is <hi>God</hi> vnto his <hi>Creatures,</hi> that hee neuer takes aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> where he beholds a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of performance.</p>
               <p>I may here then direct my ſpeech in generall to all that are here preſent, who ſhall at any time vndertake the <hi>Commiſsion</hi> of <hi>Ioſhua:</hi> Let
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15534:11"/> them be aſſured, that if <hi>God</hi> hath giuen them their <hi>Authority</hi> with a <hi>Haue not I commanded thee?</hi> the ſame <hi>God</hi> will alſo giue them the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, I will be with thee.</hi> There is none heere but my ſpeech muſt addreſſe it ſelfe vnto. Thoſe that only walke in the Streets, vnleſſe <hi>God</hi> hath giuen them his <hi>Promiſe,</hi> to <hi>bee with them,</hi> may feele his <hi>Iudgements</hi> by ſeuerall chances. Thoſe that ride abroad without this <hi>Promiſe,</hi> may dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heare of the ſeuerall <hi>afflictions,</hi> which they, aſwell as others, haue beene, or may be bitten with. But more particularly <hi>We,</hi> whoſe intent it is (with <hi>Gods</hi> aſsiſtance) to plough vp the foamie Billowes of the vaſt <hi>Ocean;</hi> whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions haue commanded to viſite another World, (as <hi>Geographers</hi> haue termed it) <hi>Wee</hi> (I ſay) muſt firſt be ſure that our <hi>Commiſsion</hi> runs in the words of my <hi>Text, Haue not I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee?</hi> and then doubt not but the <hi>Promiſe</hi> will enſue vpon it, <hi>I will be with thee. I will be with thee, Ioſhua,</hi> not at this time onely, but for euer; and not in this <hi>place</hi> onely, but <hi>whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou goeſt.</hi> Which is</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:15534:12"/>
               <head>The large Extenſion of the Promiſe: <hi>and comes next in order to be handled.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALl the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in him are <hi>Yea,</hi> and in him <hi>Amen,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.) So certaine is the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, ſo ſure the <hi>execution</hi> of them, that it tranſcends all humane Capacity, to expreſſe the truth of them. He that can doe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer he pleaſeth, cannot promiſe but what hee will <hi>performe.</hi> Whether it be in his <hi>furie,</hi> as the <hi>Plagues</hi> he ſent vpon <hi>Aegypt,</hi> vpon <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and all his <hi>houſehold:</hi> Or whether it be in <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> as the deliuering of <hi>Lot:</hi> Or meerely in his indulgent and <hi>fatherly Loue,</hi> as to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in my <hi>Text.</hi> But it may ſeeme ſtrange that <hi>God</hi> ſhould firſt command <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to goe with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and yet promiſe him to <hi>be with him whitherſoeuer he went.</hi> Obſerue we then that the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> concerning this <hi>Life,</hi> are alwaies conditionall. <hi>If ye conſent and obey, ye ſhall eate the good things of the Land: But if ye refuſe and be rebellious, ye ſhall be deuoured with the Sword.</hi> And (as it is in my <hi>Text) Onely be ſtrong, and of a good courage, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>God</hi> promiſed to <hi>be with him whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoeuer he went,</hi> prouided alwaies that hee went no whither, but to the <hi>Places</hi> where <hi>God</hi> ſhould ſend him. For <hi>Ionas</hi> ſteering his <hi>Courſe</hi> another way, when he was ſent to <hi>Nineueh,</hi> felt the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God working vpon the waters:</hi> yea, and his <hi>Protection</hi> alſo to bring him ſafely <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:15534:12"/> that he might learne a better <hi>obedience.</hi> And if <hi>Ioſhua</hi> here, in paſsing ouer <hi>Iordan,</hi> ſhape not his <hi>Courſe</hi> for the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> he may likewiſe finde that <hi>God will be with him whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he goes,</hi> either as a <hi>Iudge</hi> to <hi>puniſh,</hi> or as an <hi>Omnipotent God,</hi> to bring him backe, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the <hi>Land of Promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus will <hi>God</hi> be with <hi>Vs</hi> too, <hi>whitherſoeuer we goe.</hi> If we repaire to his <hi>Temple</hi> with <hi>honeſt hearts,</hi> and truly-religious <hi>intentions, he will bee with vs</hi> in our <hi>Prayers,</hi> and adde <hi>zeale</hi> and <hi>deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> vnto them. <hi>He will be with vs</hi> at <hi>Sermons,</hi> and adde <hi>Attention</hi> and <hi>Memory</hi> vnto <hi>vs. Hee will be with vs</hi> at the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Bodie</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of our <hi>Redeemer,</hi> and fit vs for it with <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> yea and with all other neceſſarie <hi>duties:</hi> that ſo when wee returne home to our <hi>houſes, he may be then</hi> alſo <hi>with vs,</hi> in our <hi>Practiſe</hi> of the former pious <hi>Duties;</hi> yea all our <hi>life</hi> time, by his <hi>Protection;</hi> at our <hi>deaths</hi> by <hi>Comfort;</hi> and after that in <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The thickneſſe of the <hi>Hils</hi> cannot withſtand the <hi>Immenſitie</hi> of the <hi>God-head;</hi> inſomuch that they which ſhall repaire to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſhelter, ſhall finde the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> verified; <hi>All the Mountaines are his, and the ſtrength of the Hils is his alſo.</hi> If they ſay that the <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> of the night ſhall couer them, they ſhall find that <hi>The Darkneſſe is no Darkneſſe with God,</hi> but the <hi>Night</hi> is as cleere as the <hi>Day:</hi> The <hi>Darkneſſe</hi> and the <hi>Light</hi> to him are both alike. <hi>Hell</hi> feeles the <hi>Seueritie</hi> of his <hi>Iuſtice: Earth</hi> knowes the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15534:13"/> 
                  <hi>Power</hi> of his <hi>Greatneſſe:</hi> and <hi>Heauen</hi> is filled with the bounteous <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of his <hi>Mercie.</hi> Thus is <hi>he with vs here,</hi> to <hi>ouerſee vs:</hi> in <hi>Heauen,</hi> to <hi>Crowne vs:</hi> and in <hi>Hell,</hi> to <hi>torment</hi> the <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</hi> What manner of perſons then ought we to be in all holineſſe and vprightneſſe of <hi>life?</hi> He that runs on in his <hi>Sinnes</hi> (iuſt like a <hi>Moath</hi> about the <hi>Candle</hi> in the night) playes with <hi>hell-fire,</hi> till at laſt it conſumes him. He that makes a profeſſion of <hi>holineſse,</hi> and ſeemes to endeuor to be as he appeares, yet harbouring ſtill ſome <hi>boſome-ſinne,</hi> imitates a <hi>Fly</hi> ſhut vp in a <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> at noone day, which beholding the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light through the glaſſe, beates it ſelfe to death againſt that which diſcouers the light: But he whoſe <hi>heart</hi> is vpright, and <hi>conuerſation</hi> iuſt, flies vp in his <hi>Meditations</hi> to the <hi>higheſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens,</hi> to prepare a place for what is yet impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon Earth. Whenſoeuer hee ſtayes at home, hee findes <hi>God</hi> there, and for the time makes it a <hi>Bethel:</hi> when he goes abroad, (with <hi>Iacob</hi>) he findes <hi>God</hi> there too, and ſets vp a <hi>Piller</hi> of <hi>Praiers,</hi> to make it the <hi>Gate</hi> of <hi>Heauen.</hi> When he ſleepes, he is clambering vpon <hi>Iacobs Ladder</hi> vp to <hi>Heauen:</hi> And when he wakes, he finds <hi>God with him</hi> then too, ready to accept of his <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and protect him vnder the ſhadow of his wings. The whole <hi>Vniuerſe</hi> can as eaſily teach vs the <hi>Omni-preſence,</hi> as the <hi>Omni-potencie</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and confound the Aſſertions of <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Infidelity. Ioſhua</hi> therfore here durſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> whether hee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15534:13"/> 
                  <hi>could be with him,</hi> nor his <hi>Truth,</hi> whether hee <hi>would be with him whitherſoeuer he went.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus muſt we then with <hi>Ioſhua</hi> reſolue to <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,</hi> that we may ſecure our <hi>happineſse. God will be with vs,</hi> if he promiſe it. GOD will promiſe it, if we deſire it; but without that, no <hi>Promiſe,</hi> nor fauourable <hi>Preſence.</hi> GOD <hi>will be with vs</hi> in <hi>Peace,</hi> to preſerue <hi>vs</hi> in <hi>vnity:</hi> in the <hi>Warres,</hi> to <hi>giue vs</hi> the <hi>Victorie:</hi> in our <hi>Natiue Soile,</hi> to bleſſe <hi>vs</hi> with <hi>Plentie;</hi> and in <hi>forraigne-parts,</hi> to enrich vs with <hi>Proſperity;</hi> prouided alwaies that (with <hi>Ioſhua</hi>) wee receiue our <hi>Command</hi> from the GOD of <hi>Heauen.</hi> But if being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, we runne into <hi>diſobedience;</hi> our <hi>Peace</hi> ſhall bee corrupted with perpetuall Alarums; our <hi>Warres</hi> ſhall deuoure vs; our owne <hi>Country</hi> ſhall lye waſte; and when we ſeeke <hi>abroad,</hi> we ſhall periſh where none ſhall haue compaſſion on <hi>vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let <hi>vs</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more eſpecially, which muſt looke vndaunted vpon <hi>Death</hi> it ſelfe, by the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our <hi>Maker,</hi> and ſee his <hi>workes</hi> of <hi>wonder</hi> in the <hi>Deepes;</hi> that muſt flye from hence vpon the <hi>wings</hi> of the <hi>Wind</hi> to the <hi>waſt places of the Earth,</hi> to plant the knowledge of his <hi>goodnes</hi> who commands vs to goe; Let <hi>vs</hi> (I ſay) more eſpecially aſſure our ſelues that we are diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Ioſhuas Commiſsion,</hi> that the <hi>Sea</hi> may be but a <hi>Iordan</hi> vnto <hi>vs,</hi> and the <hi>Land</hi> we goe to inhabit, a <hi>Canaan.</hi> Our <hi>examples</hi> muſt as much teach the <hi>Saluages what</hi> we <hi>obey,</hi> as our <hi>Precepts, whom</hi> we <hi>obey.</hi> Our <hi>Religion</hi> muſt be aſwell clad
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15534:14"/> in <hi>Sinceritie,</hi> as our <hi>Strength</hi> in <hi>Courage;</hi> that ſo thoſe <hi>ignorant Infidels</hi> obſeruing our religious <hi>Conuerſation,</hi> may ioyne with vs in a happy <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution.</hi> Our equall Steps, and vpright beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uior thus inflaming the hearts of the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> it may peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture proue in a ſhort ſpace, a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taſte to diſſwade them from beleeuing <hi>vs</hi> to be <hi>Gods,</hi> then to perſwade them to beleeue that there is a <hi>God.</hi> Thus may thoſe which are yet <hi>without,</hi> be comforted, &amp; may perceiue that <hi>God is with vs whitherſoeuer we goe.</hi> It was his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> and doubtleſſe it is the ſame to <hi>vs;</hi> the <hi>Conditions</hi> aſwell as the <hi>Commiſsion</hi> ſtill running alike, <hi>Onely be ſtrong and of a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: Be not afraid, neither be diſmaid.</hi> Which is</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Generall: The Perſon comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Ioſhua. <hi>Wherein firſt of the</hi> Affirmatiue part: Be ſtrong, and of a good courage.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAns Integrity</hi> was the <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> but his <hi>Fall</hi> the <hi>ruine</hi> thereof. When GOD impoſed this <hi>Taxe</hi> vpon the <hi>Creatures</hi> for <hi>Adams diſobedience,</hi> all things tumultuouſly ſtole into a <hi>Mutinie.</hi> The <hi>Earth</hi> ſuddenly hatched an <hi>abortiue Contention,</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the <hi>Thornes</hi> and <hi>Thiſtles</hi> witneſſed their <hi>ſtrife,</hi> by a greedy ſcratching of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>Elements</hi> not contented with <hi>Peace,</hi> fell at variance too, ſo that the <hi>Fire</hi> wanting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to ouercome the <hi>Water</hi> hiſſed at the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour:</hi> and that part of <hi>Ayre</hi> which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15534:14"/> in the bowels of the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſhooke the foundation when it triumphed in a <hi>Victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ouid Meta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Frigida pugnabunt calidis, humentia ſiccis,</l>
                  <l>Ouid Meta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Mollia cum duris, ſine po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia pondus.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Yea, and to ſhew the corruption that wee our ſelues fell into, the whole <hi>World</hi> ſeeming (as it were) too little to containe two <hi>Brothers, Abels</hi> blood muſt be the price of <hi>Caines</hi> reuenge. Hence haue our <hi>Wars</hi> drawne their ſucceſſion, and the gaining of <hi>Kingdomes</hi> hath become the large rate of innocent Blood: yet all to proue the <hi>Iuſtice</hi> of our <hi>Maker,</hi> who ſeeing vs neglect his <hi>Commandements,</hi> giues vs ouer to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed one of another. But as in other things, ſo in this, is his <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> manifeſted too, in that he puniſhes <hi>Rebellion</hi> with <hi>extirpation;</hi> &amp; makes <hi>Religion</hi> inherit, where ſpotted <hi>Vice</hi> ſeekes its <hi>ſubuerſion.</hi> It is apparant by thoſe whom the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are ſent to ſupplant. <hi>The Canaanites,</hi> which liued in the height of <hi>ſenſuality,</hi> muſt be humbled now in the depth of <hi>Miſerie.</hi> The great <hi>Law-giuer</hi> obſerues ſuch a legall courſe in his <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that whom <hi>Plenty</hi> hath ſwelled vp to the diſeaſe of <hi>wickedneſſe, Pouerty</hi> ſhall bee Phyſicke to bring them to <hi>humility.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, Thoſe that haue ſuffered the Slauerie of Bondage, to be free for his Seruice, ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit a <hi>Canaan,</hi> to encourage them in their <hi>Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> which were expoſed to the tyrannie of <hi>injuſtice</hi> vnder the <hi>Aegyptian Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roah,</hi> muſt be comforted againe with <hi>Milke</hi> and <hi>Honey.</hi> But leſt a ſodaine <hi>Liberty</hi> ſhould
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15534:15"/> procure their forgetfulnes of <hi>him</hi> that relieued them in <hi>miſerie,</hi> a tedious <hi>Iourney</hi> muſt vſher them to <hi>Repoſe.</hi> They are come neere <hi>Iordan,</hi> and their <hi>Commander</hi> (poore wretches) ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders vp his <hi>Soule</hi> to the <hi>Giuer thereof.</hi> Yet no ſooner is he deceaſed, then <hi>Ioſhua</hi> is raiſed. And leſt hee ſhould pleade excuſe through a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Infidelity, <hi>Moſes</hi> before his death (<hi>Deut.</hi> 31.6.) encourages him, ſaying, <hi>Bee ſtrong, and of a good courage: Bee not afraid, neither be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid,</hi> for thy <hi>Lord</hi> thy <hi>God</hi> it is he that doth go with <hi>thee,</hi> he will not faile <hi>thee,</hi> nor forſake <hi>thee.</hi> The <hi>Injunction</hi> from <hi>Heauen</hi> ſtill remaines the ſame, <hi>Be ſtrong, and of a good courage.</hi> Yea, and to the intent that <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſhould neither forget nor ſlight his <hi>Charge,</hi> it is oftentimes repeated; as you may reade in the 6. and 7. verſes of the 31. Chap. of <hi>Deut.</hi> and in the 6, 7, 9, and 18. verſes of this Chapter. Where <hi>God</hi> is vrgent in preſſing <hi>Man</hi> to his <hi>dutie,</hi> his <hi>Puniſhments</hi> for <hi>neglect</hi> become the greater. <hi>Ioſhua</hi> certainely cannot forget what he is ſo often charged; he cannot deny it, becauſe the <hi>Command</hi> is from <hi>Heauen:</hi> and he muſt not diſobey it, for now his Credit, his Obſeruance, and his Reward lye at the ſtake. Durſt any to queſtion what need the <hi>All-mighty</hi> had to preſſe <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſo hard to it, whom he could with a word make ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily valiant: the anſwer is ready, That hee is not alwaies pleaſed to doe what he can, becauſe he will try (as it were) whether men are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe what they may.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:15534:15"/>
               <p>But ſhall he command <hi>Ioſhua</hi> to bee <hi>ſtrong,</hi> who hath ſaid himſelfe, that hee <hi>delighteth</hi> not in any mans <hi>Strength?</hi> Alas (Beloued) <hi>What haue wee which wee haue not receiued from him?</hi> If I ſpeake of <hi>ſtrength; Loe hee is ſtrong</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>Iob, chap.</hi> 9.19.) wherefore whomſoeuer he commandeth to <hi>be ſtrong,</hi> his very Word <hi>ſtrengthens</hi> both the <hi>command</hi> and the <hi>comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi> But becauſe ye ſhould not run blindfold in an error, &amp; be muffled with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinion of the World, intituling euery raſh and immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate heate with the name of <hi>valour,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> ſhall rectifie your iudgements.</p>
               <p>If ye pleaſe to attend to <hi>Ariſt:</hi> ye ſhall heare him call it the <hi>ruſhing vpon things terrible, where Death ſtands ready to ſnatch vs, yet we vndergoe the ieopardy for ſome common-good. Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> determines it to be <hi>A habit of the minde, whereby according to a right reaſon, and for ſome iuſt and lawfull end, wee hold a meane betweene Feare and Audaciouſneſſe.</hi> Others affirme it to be the <hi>Defender of Iuſtice, whereby wee either ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Aduerſity, or moderate our Griefe in affliction, or curbe our ioy in Proſperity, leſt exceſſe of Ioy or Sorrow ſhould breed the performance of that which is baſe and wicked.</hi> Take which <hi>definition</hi> you pleaſe, or ioine them together, &amp; I ſuppoſe it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in brief for a preſent knowledge. Should I but attempt to diuide it, the time would faile me before I ſhould find the way out againe. The of it howſoeuer is ſomthing which is <hi>honeſt</hi> &amp; <hi>good,</hi> otherwiſe it is ſtyled <hi>madneſſe</hi> and <hi>cruelty.</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15534:16"/> That which is thus <hi>good</hi> and <hi>honeſt,</hi> is either for <hi>God,</hi> our <hi>Country,</hi> or our <hi>King.</hi> The <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>Valour</hi> is that part of the <hi>Minde</hi> wherein (in the abſence of it) <hi>Feare</hi> or <hi>Audacity</hi> keep their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The <hi>Object</hi> that it lookes vpon is <hi>Danger.</hi> The <hi>Forme</hi> of it is a <hi>Meane</hi> betweene the two <hi>Contraries:</hi> and the true <hi>end,</hi> in briefe, is that which is well-pleaſing to <hi>God.</hi> It is wrought in <hi>vs,</hi> and becomes <hi>ours</hi> in this manner.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>God</hi> opens our <hi>vnderſtandings,</hi> and teacheth vs that he is moſt happie, who <hi>ſuffers</hi> moſt for his ſake.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>He is with vs</hi> by his <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly and laſtly, <hi>He ſends his holy Spirit</hi> to cheere vs vp, that we may boldly ſuffer what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer befals vs.</p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernard</hi> would haue euery <hi>valiant mans Action</hi> be thus tempered; <hi>Sit Iuſtitia</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in affectu, Prudentia in intellectu, Fortitudo in effectu, &amp; Temperantia in vſu.</hi> There muſt bee <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in our <hi>affection; Wiſdome</hi> in our <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; Courage</hi> in the <hi>eff cting</hi> of it; and <hi>Temperance</hi> or <hi>Moderation</hi> in the <hi>vſe</hi> of it. See then how boldly he may fall-on, whom GOD commands to be <hi>ſtrong,</hi> and of a <hi>good courage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let me not forget the <hi>raſhneſſe</hi> of our <hi>Age,</hi> which writes him <hi>Valiant,</hi> that dares thruſt himſelfe into a <hi>Challenge</hi> for a ſlight <hi>offence,</hi> and hazard his <hi>Soule</hi> for the ſteame of a <hi>word. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> cannot pleade excuſe for him who mortga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that <hi>Iewell</hi> for the vanity of a word, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15534:16"/> coſt our <hi>Sauiour</hi> the price of Blood. <hi>He</hi> came to loſe his <hi>Life</hi> for our ſakes, and ſhall we quit our ſelues of our ſelues for a blaſt ſhorter then our Breath? In the <hi>reuengefull</hi> perſon, if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe may ſpeake, <hi>verba verbis expianda,</hi> words ſhould expiate words: But in the <hi>rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate</hi> man, neither <hi>words</hi> nor <hi>actions</hi> can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile for <hi>Reuenge,</hi> becauſe <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will repay it,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Lord.</hi>) Yet miſtake me not (Beloued) For as we ought to be cowardly in the performance of things prohibited, ſo ſhould we ſtriue for <hi>valour</hi> in the execution of that which is <hi>iuſt.</hi> When I condemne euery common <hi>Duell,</hi> I approue of our lawfull <hi>Wars;</hi> and where the <hi>Souldier</hi> fights vpon <hi>iuſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> that man is either ignorantly fillie, or miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably deteſtable that honours not the <hi>Calling.</hi> The ſlight reward which the noble <hi>Souldier</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues from the mouths of many in this <hi>age,</hi> may ſtrike vs into a feare leſt we ſhall hereafter cry for <hi>thoſe</hi> whom wee now deſpiſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the want of whom our Griefe cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. But <hi>God</hi> of his <hi>mercy</hi> preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it by his <hi>Power,</hi> and preſerue vs ſafe from the <hi>furie</hi> of our <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> O it is (me thinks) a poore, and ſhamefull requitall for the ineffable miſeries and hazards which a <hi>Souldier</hi> ſuffers abroad, when at home hee ſhall bee bitten with the <hi>aſpine Tongues</hi> of ſome venemous <hi>Cowards</hi> whoſe property it is to vnder-value what they dare not vnder-goe. Theſe are ſtrong indeede, but onely in their poyſonous Breath, and their good <hi>courage</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:15534:17"/> proues <hi>Pedancie</hi> expreſſing it ſelfe in a ſpeedy flight, not ſtanding the ſhocke of <hi>oppoſition.</hi> I could be farre more copious in the iuſt proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, but that the time would preuent me: Howſoeuer, giue me leaue to admoniſh the <hi>Souldier</hi> too, that he may know that ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Oathes,</hi> prophane and execrable <hi>Curſes,</hi> and ſurfeiting vpon all vncleane and ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous filthineſſe, diſgraces the <hi>Perſon,</hi> and reflects in part vpon the <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> not without a ſtaine of <hi>Reproach.</hi> They ſurely cannot be <hi>ſtrong, and of a good courage,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>vice,</hi> not <hi>order</hi> inſtructs in vndigeſted <hi>raſhnes.</hi> It is <hi>Ioſhua</hi> only that is <hi>ſtrong, &amp; of a good courage,</hi> becauſe his <hi>Cauſe</hi> is <hi>iuſt,</hi> his <hi>conſcience vpright,</hi> his <hi>Religion Zealous,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> his <hi>Protector;</hi> for <hi>vice</hi> and <hi>valour</hi> neuer yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in one. O let vs then, who (as I hope) are all <hi>Ioſhuas,</hi> holy and religious, <hi>be ſtrong and of a good courage,</hi> that we may neither <hi>feare the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that flyeth by day,</hi> nor the <hi>Inſtruments of War</hi> that ſpeake in fury: for <hi>Dauid</hi> may kill <hi>Goliah; Saul may ſlay his thouſand, &amp; Dauid his ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>God giues the word, to be ſtrong, &amp;c.</hi> He that enioines vs to it, can and will expect our <hi>performance;</hi> and requires that whom he <hi>che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes,</hi> ſhould not <hi>be afraid, neither bee diſmaid.</hi> Which is</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:15534:17"/>
               <head>The Negatiue part <hi>required in</hi> Ioſhua, <hi>my laſt point, and craues your patience for a little while.</hi> Feare not, neither be diſmaid.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COntraria iuxta ſe poſita, magis eluceſcunt.</hi> Contraries then appeare moſt manifeſt when they are neerely ioyned each to other, as in <hi>blacke</hi> and <hi>white; heate</hi> and <hi>cold,</hi> and the like. Right ſo is it here: for <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>diſmay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> are but the priuation of <hi>valour</hi> and <hi>courage,</hi> (handled in the firſt point.) I ſhall not neede to dwell long vpon it. Only take the <hi>definition</hi> of it from <hi>Ariſt:</hi> out of the ſecond of his <hi>Rhet.</hi> where he determines it to be <hi>A certaine Griefe and trembling of the Mind,</hi> ariſing from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious thought of ſome inſuing <hi>Euill,</hi> which may bring vpon vs either <hi>Trouble</hi> or <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> Should then a <hi>Ioſhua feare,</hi> hee might ſuffer the cenſure of men, and the diſpleaſure of <hi>God,</hi> for want of confidence in him that imployes him. <hi>Dangers</hi> he muſt needs vndergoe, that runs the hazard of <hi>Trauels</hi> and <hi>Warre:</hi> But where GOD commands vs not to bee <hi>afraid,</hi> the <hi>Perils</hi> are preuented by the word of <hi>authority.</hi> Should <hi>Ioſhua feare</hi> the <hi>wounds</hi> hee might perhaps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from his <hi>Enemies;</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> is that good <hi>Samaritane</hi> that can powre <hi>Oyle</hi> into them. Should the feare of a <hi>Dearth</hi> poſſeſſe him; alas, <hi>the Lions doe lacke, and ſuffer hunger; but they that trust in the Lord ſhall want no manner of thing that is good.</hi> Should he feare the <hi>pangs</hi> of a dry and ſcorching <hi>Thirſt; He</hi> that before opened
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15534:18"/> the <hi>Rocke, and the waters guſhed out,</hi> is as power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full now as he was at that time. Nay, ſhould he feare <hi>Death</hi> it ſelfe, it might be an argument to proue the badneſſe of his life; or at leaſt it might giue a ſuſpition of their <hi>vnbeliefe</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that happieſt life of <hi>Glorie.</hi> To ſuſpect a <hi>danger</hi> before it comes, is to ruſh into <hi>Miſery</hi> before our times: and ſo inſtead of preuention to haſten the deſtruction. <hi>Quid prodeſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Sen.) mala arceſſere &amp; praeſens tempus futuri metu perdere? Stultum eſt, quaſi ante futurus miſer, eſse iam miſerum:</hi> He that ſtriues to preuent a <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe,</hi> and yet loſes the preſent time in the <hi>feare</hi> of that which is to come, fals wretched before it was appointed for him. Why ſhould <hi>Ioſhua</hi> then feare, or <hi>be diſmaid,</hi> whom <hi>God almighty</hi> promiſeth to preſerue? <hi>Ignorat gratiam liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quem ligat ſeruitus timoris,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Greg.</hi>) He knowes not the bleſſing of <hi>Libertie,</hi> which lies impriſoned in the bondage of <hi>Feare.</hi> Let them be <hi>diſmaid,</hi> whoſe ſicke <hi>Soules,</hi> deepe in a Conſumption, forget to hope for a future re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. <hi>Integer vitae ſceleriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> purus, non eget Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri iaculis, nec arcu.</hi> A pure and vndefiled <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> needs no <hi>Shield</hi> to guard it from the fury of an <hi>Aduerſary. Ioſhua</hi> may well <hi>feare</hi> if once he <hi>diſobey,</hi> but till then let him be afraid to <hi>feare,</hi> leſt thereby he be <hi>diſmaid.</hi> Should we attribute the <hi>euent of Warre</hi> to <hi>Fortune,</hi> the <hi>Heathen Poet</hi> would encourage the dulleſt ſpirit. <hi>Fortuna for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes metuit, Ignauos premit,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Senec.) For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> ſtands afraid of thoſe that are <hi>valiant,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15534:18"/> but plaies vpon the <hi>Cowards.</hi> Yet we that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the vanity of that <hi>heatheniſh</hi> Idoll, muſt confeſſe with <hi>Salomon,</hi> that <hi>The Horſe is prepared for Battell, but God giueth the Victorie. (Pro.</hi> 22.31.) Yet it may appeare ſtrange, that <hi>God</hi> ſhould command <hi>Ioſhua</hi> not to <hi>feare,</hi> when as his <hi>Statutes</hi> run perpetually, <hi>Feare ye the Lord.</hi> There is indeed a twofold <hi>feare, Filiall,</hi> and <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile:</hi> the former ariſing from a true affection we beare to our <hi>Creator,</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> to offend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we <hi>loue</hi> him. The latter is onely a <hi>feare</hi> of the <hi>euill</hi> of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> ariſing from a <hi>guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> The former is commanded, the latter forbidden in my <hi>Text.</hi> But this is a baſe <hi>feare</hi> of our <hi>Enemies,</hi> not to be ſuffered. The <hi>Heathen</hi> were as ignorant of the <hi>Puniſhments</hi> which came from <hi>God,</hi> as ſent by him, as they were of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe; and therefore one of their <hi>Poets,</hi> out of a daring reſolution, cries out, <hi>Moriamur, &amp; in media arma ruamus, vna ſalus victis nullam ſperare ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Let vs <hi>die,</hi> (ſaies he) and ruſh into the midſt of our <hi>Enemies;</hi> the only <hi>ſafety</hi> the <hi>conquered</hi> know, is to haue no <hi>ſafety.</hi> Shall then the <hi>Heathen</hi> out-doe <hi>vs,</hi> in that which <hi>Religion</hi> teaches vs to be perfect? No, (Beloued) let <hi>vs</hi> goe on valiantly and couragiouſly when wee haue occaſion, for the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God will be with vs whitherſoeuer we goe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You that liue at home <hi>vnder your owne Vines,</hi> and eate the <hi>fruites</hi> of your owne <hi>Trees;</hi> that feele not the terror of <hi>want,</hi> nor the heate of <hi>Miſeries,</hi> to you it belongs to be <hi>valiant</hi> in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15534:19"/> (if occaſion ſhall happen) any <hi>perſecution</hi> or <hi>croſse</hi> which <hi>God</hi> may iuſtly inflict vpon you, either as a <hi>Puniſhment</hi> or <hi>Tryal.</hi> Beſides ye muſt be <hi>valiant</hi> in the <hi>Conflict</hi> againſt the <hi>World,</hi> the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the <hi>Deuill,</hi> leſt if they ouercome, <hi>deſtruction ſodainely come vpon you, as ſorrow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Woman in trauell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe, for <hi>vs</hi> that go abroad, it belongs in a ſpeciall manner not to <hi>be afraid, neither bee diſmaid.</hi> If the ſurging waues of a ſwelling <hi>Sea</hi> ſmoke out <hi>threats</hi> and <hi>anger,</hi> yet <hi>he that walked vpon the water and breathed a calme,</hi> can doe the like for vs too; but we muſt not <hi>be afraid, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be diſmaid.</hi> When the tempeſtuous <hi>Winds</hi> buzze in our eares, and ſeeme to ſpeake the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>death, he</hi> that once charm'd them with <hi>Peace; be ſtill;</hi> can doe the like for <hi>vs</hi> too; but <hi>we</hi> muſt not <hi>feare</hi> then, <hi>neither be diſmaid.</hi> If the bluſtring noiſe of <hi>Guns</hi> ſhall roare in our eares, to threaten our mangling ſubuerſion, yet <hi>hee</hi> that taught our <hi>Enemies</hi> to <hi>war,</hi> and <hi>their fingers to fight,</hi> can aſwell vnteach them againe, and ſtrike them with aſtoniſhment for our ſakes; but he ſtill requires that we ſhould <hi>not be afraid, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be diſmaid.</hi> Laſtly, if the <hi>Companie</hi> of <hi>Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Archers</hi> ranke themſelues againſt vs, yea and promiſe to themſelues our vtter confuſion; yet muſt we know that the <hi>Lord,</hi> which is <hi>a Man of War,</hi> (as he hath ſtiled himſelfe) <hi>which breaketh the Bow in pieces, and knappeth the Arrowes in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> can preuent their <hi>furie;</hi> but his <hi>Charge</hi> ſtill will remaine the ſame; the ſame <hi>Condition,</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:15534:19"/> that <hi>wee bee not afraid, neither bee diſmaid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let me adde then S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> words of <hi>Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Deus tibi totum eſt; ſi ſitias, Aqua tibi eſt; ſi in Tenebris ſis, Lumen tibi eſt; ac ſi nudus, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitatis tibi Veſtis eſt. God</hi> will be all in all vnto thee; If thou art hungry, he will be <hi>Bread</hi> vnto thee; if thirſty, <hi>Water;</hi> if thou ſitteſt in <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> he will <hi>ſhine</hi> vpon thee; and if thou art naked, he will cloathe thee with <hi>Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> O let vs then, who intend (by the <hi>diuine Prouidence</hi>) to <hi>ſing the Lords Song, in a ſtrange Land,</hi> here make our promiſe vnto the <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, That he ſhall be the Lord our God, and him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone will we ſerue.</hi> And then the <hi>Lord</hi> will ſpeake vnto <hi>vs,</hi> as he did to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> in the words of my <hi>Text, Haue not I commanded thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before we depart, it remaines that the <hi>Teſtimonie</hi> of our <hi>Faith, Repentance, Loue, Zeale,</hi> and all other <hi>diuine Graces</hi> be ſealed here in the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Congregation.</hi> See how for our <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Chriſt</hi> hath inuited vs all vnto a <hi>Feaſt;</hi> O let <hi>vs</hi> draw neere, and receiue our ſweet <hi>Ieſus</hi> into the boſomes of our <hi>Soules,</hi> that he may receiue vs into the Armes of his <hi>Mercie:</hi> Our louing <hi>Sauiour</hi> did eate of the <hi>Bread of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that we might eate of the <hi>Bread of Life:</hi> Our <hi>Ieſus</hi> drunke of the <hi>Waters</hi> of <hi>Marah,</hi> that wee might drinke of the ſweet Springs of <hi>Liuing-Water.</hi> Come, let vs <hi>feaſt</hi> then both with him, and on him, that <hi>faſted</hi> for vs; Let vs embrace him with <hi>reuerence;</hi> hold him by <hi>faith;</hi> keepe him with <hi>charity;</hi> and preſerue him in our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15534:20"/> 
                  <hi>ſoules,</hi> with <hi>repentance</hi> for our <hi>wrongs</hi> paſt, and <hi>Praiers</hi> and ſtriuing againſt it for time to come; that his <hi>victorious Death</hi> may be to <hi>vs</hi> a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <hi>Life.</hi> Thus when we haue all <hi>eaten</hi> and <hi>dranke</hi> together the <hi>aſſurance</hi> of our <hi>Adoption</hi> and <hi>Saluation,</hi> let vs depart in <hi>Peace,</hi> with <hi>Ioy</hi> in the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But firſt, to thoſe that remaine in this flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing <hi>Kingdome,</hi> We will cry, <hi>Peace be within your Walls, and Plenteouſneſſe within your Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; For our Brethren and Companions ſakes, we will wiſh you Proſperity.</hi> For <hi>vs,</hi> that muſt ariſe, and ſeeke out a farther <hi>habitation,</hi> we will beg of the <hi>Almighty</hi> with a vnanimous conſent, that he will be graciouſly pleaſed to ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>vs,</hi> in the words of my <hi>Text: Haue not I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you? Onely be ſtrong, and of a good cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: Be not afraid, neither be diſmaid, for I will be with you whitherſoeuer ye goe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to all of <hi>vs</hi> may the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly giue and beſtow his <hi>Bleſſings,</hi> that wee may not want his louing <hi>Protection</hi> in this <hi>Life,</hi> nor the fruition of <hi>Glory</hi> together in the <hi>Life</hi> to come.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which God of his infinite Mercie grant, &amp;c. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15534:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
